<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Guild-Hall chapel, December the xi, 1692 before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, and Court of Aldermen / by W. Fleetwood ...</title>
            <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20983</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12565789</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12565789</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39742)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 691:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Guild-Hall chapel, December the xi, 1692 before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, and Court of Aldermen / by W. Fleetwood ...</title>
                  <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 5-29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Newborough ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title: Mr. Fleetwood's sermon before the Lord Mayor, &amp;c. December xi, 1692.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes VI, 11-12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:63324:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63324:1"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>FLEETWOOD</hi>'s SERMON BEFORE THE LORD MAYOR, <hi>&amp;c. DECEMBER</hi> xi. 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:63324:2"/>
            <head>Fleet Mayor.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Martis xiij<hi rend="sup">o</hi> Die Decemb' 1692. Anno<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Regis &amp; Reginae, Will. &amp; Mariae, Angl.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> to Print his SERMON, Preached at the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chapel, on <hi>Sunday</hi> laſt, before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GOODFELLOW.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63324:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at <hi>GUILD-HALL</hi> Chapel, <hi>DECEMBER</hi> the xi. 1692. BEFORE THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THE LORD MAYOR, AND <hi>Court of Aldermen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. FLEETWOOD,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to their MAJESTIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Newborough,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-Yard, 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:63324:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63324:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ECCLES. vi. 11, 12.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeing there be many things that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Vanity, what is Man the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For who knoweth what is good for Man in this Life, all the Days of his vain Life which he ſpendeth as a Shadow? for who can tell a Man what ſhall be after him, under the Sun?</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE great End and Deſign of King <hi>Solomon</hi> in this Book, is, to ſhew wherein conſiſts the true and laſting Happineſs of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; which he in ſhort comprizes <hi>in the Fearing God and Keeping his Commandments.</hi> But knowing the World was old, and had been long in full Poſſeſſion of another ſort of Notions and Conceits of Happineſs than what he came to teach, he found it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, firſt to undeceive it of its Errors, correct its wide Miſtakes, and root up its ill founded Prejudices,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63324:4"/> and Prepoſſeſſions in this Matter. And to this end, the Preacher (as he calls himſelf) well knowing 'twas as hard a Task to unlearn an old Miſtake, as to take up a Leſſon of new Truth, ſpends half his Sermon, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering to the World the Emptineſs and Vanity of thoſe four great Ends in which the Generality of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind had concurr'd to place their chief Felicity, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Wiſdom, Pleaſures, Honours,</hi> or in <hi>Riches;</hi> on each of which he argues from particular Miſchiefs and Diſſatisfactions, and irreſiſtibly concludes, That each of them was <hi>Vanity and Vexation of Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was the fitteſt Man to paſs this decretory Sentence and deciſive Judgment, that ever yet was born into this World, of humane Parents. For tho' there have been Princes of as diſſolute a Soul, and as unbounded Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as <hi>Solomon;</hi> although there have been Princes that have rais'd their Slaves and Bondmen to Dignities and Wealth, that far ſurpaſs'd the Glory and the Riches of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and of <hi>Judab</hi> both together; yet none of them were ever fitted equally with <hi>Solomon,</hi> to give a true Account and Character of either Pleaſure, Wealth or Honours, becauſe they wanted Wiſdom with the reſt, and conſequently neither underſtood the Uſe and Worth, nor yet the Vanity and Emptineſs of thoſe Enjoyments. When we ſee a Man over-run with Pleaſures, or behave himſelf with Inſolence in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or employ his Wealth to evil Purpoſes, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conclude the Fault is in his Judgment; and, That the things themſelves, and in their own Natures, are ſuch as Men of Wiſdom and Underſtanding, may both place and find therein abundance of true and ſolid Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. But <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Experience and the Sentence that he paſſes on them, is ſufficient (one would think)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63324:4"/> to ſilence all Suggeſtions of that Nature. He was the richeſt and moſt glorious King that ever rul'd in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and made his Wealth and Power ſubſervient to his Pleaſures. And to all this the moſt conſummate Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that a humane Heart and Head is capable of bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was beſtowed upon him; beſtowed upon him at the firſt, and in an Inſtant too; not acquir'd by Art and Induſtry, nor labour'd out by long Experience; which kind of Wiſdom is commonly bought with a great deal of time, and a great many Miſcarriages and ſad Miſtakes. And of a King wiſe as the Oracles of God, and wiſe before he entered on his Wealth and Power, and Pleaſures (which never Man beſides him was,) if <hi>he</hi> pronounce this Judgment, both from the perfect Knowledge and the full Enjoyment of them all, That <hi>they are Vanity and Vexation of Spirit,</hi> there is enough, without recurring to the Infallibility of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to be certain of the Concluſion; for what he ſays elſewhere, is very applicable here; <hi>What can the Man do that cometh after the King, but that which hath been already done?</hi> The King hath tried and done all, and that with greater Aſſiſtances and more Advantages, than any Man beſides hath done; and yet declares, That <hi>all is Vanity and Vexation of Spirit;</hi> and what can any Man do after him, but try the ſame, and make the ſame Concluſion too, if he be wiſe; or rather make the ſame Concluſion, without the Tryal, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be wiſe at <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Expence.</p>
            <p>The Text is the Summ and Concluſion of all Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, the Epilogue of all theſe falſe Felicities. <hi>Seeing there be many things that encreaſe Vanity, what is Man the better?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be ſome One might object, What tho' a Man
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63324:5"/> do not find his Account in <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> it may be, the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits of it are painful without Benefit, exceeding hard to get at all, and yet of very little uſe when gotten; and it may be that Concluſion is very true, <hi>That in much Wiſdom is much Grief, and he that increaſeth Knowledge increaſeth Sorrow.</hi> Yet there are other things in which a Man may ſeek and find his Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this Life, ſuch as it may be, Pleaſure, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours or Poſſeſſions, and that if One ſhould fail a Man, Another may be ſure to make him good amends, for his Miſtakes in Judgment, or his Labour loſt in Practice. <hi>Solomon</hi> therefore (aware of this beſure) concludes them all, upon Experiment, under the ſame condemning Sentence, tells his Hearers, That certain Happineſs was not to be found in any thing of this Life: That it was never the better for Men, that there were many things and different Objects in this World to place their Happineſs upon, ſince all thoſe many things and different Objects carried their many and their differing Vanities along with them; and multiplied Vexations to their Purſuers and Poſſeſſours. What is it better for a Man to have more Occaſions to employ his Care and Induſtry upon, ſince he thereby has but the more Defeats? What is it better for a Man to have Diverſity of Objects to fix his Hopes upon, and raiſe him more and greater Expectations, ſince he thereby has only more and greater Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <p>This Verſe is capable of, and hath had other Meanings put upon it; but this ſeems both the beſt and propereſt, and connects it with what went before and what follows—For, <hi>who knoweth what is good for Man in this Life.</hi> Though there be many things,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63324:5"/> never ſo many things (which yet may be ranked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe four Heads) yet what is Man the better as to the attaining true Felicity in them, ſince they are all of them vain, and have no true Felicity belonging to them? but if they had, Man were as far from get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it as ever, ſince he is ignorant wherein it does con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and what it is, would make him happy in this Life. <hi>Who knoweth what is good for Man in this Life?</hi> The moſt exalted Underſtanding in the World, the cleareſt Foreſight and the ſtrongeſt Reaſon, with the moſt mature Judgment is commonly as much miſtaken in its Choice of what is good for Man in this Life, as he that commits it to the chance of a pair of Dice, or the Arbitration of ſome thoughtleſs Child: And that, becauſe of the Uncertainty of future Events which humane Wiſdom cannot poſſibly foreſee, and the Inſtability of things preſent, which humane Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er cannot poſſibly fix and faſten. And ſince it is not worth the Name of Happineſs, that is expos'd to ſo much Chance, and of ſuch ſhort and ſuch uncertain Duration, it is impoſſible for Man to know and chuſe what is good for him in this Life, and where to find his true Happineſs; <hi>For who can tell a Man what ſhall be after him?</hi> Who is there knows, what time to come will bring forth; whether to Morrow's Event will not ſpoil to Day's Happineſs and quite unravel the beſt knit Plots, and fruſtrate the moſt probable Deſigns that can be?</p>
            <p>The Words in general thus explained, will afford us three Propoſitions to conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">I. That though there are many things, and great Diverſity of Objects for Men to buſie themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and ſeek their Happineſs and Satisfactions in;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63324:6"/> yet it is never the better for them, becauſe they all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Vanity, they are all of them vain, and 'tis in vain to think of finding our true Happineſs in any, or in all of them.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That tho' theſe ſeveral things would really much conduce to the bettering Mens Conditions, and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to them Happineſs, yet it were never the better for them, they would be never the nearer Happineſs, becauſe no Man knows what is truly good for him in this Life, and moſt convenient to the attaining of that End.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That tho' a Man ſhould be ſo fortunate, as to light upon what was good for him at preſent, yet he would have no great reaſon to exult, becauſe his Good may be ſhort-liv'd, and change its nature in a little time; <hi>For who can tell what ſhall be after him?</hi> Of theſe in their Order. And <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Diverſity and Multitude of Objects are all of them vain, they all increaſe Vanity. And this cannot better be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, than by conſidering in ſhort the Vanity of thoſe four Heads of Wiſdom, Pleaſure, Riches and Honours; to which the World in general is devoted, in which they think to find their Happineſs, and to which all other things are eaſily reduc'd. And,</p>
            <p>I. Of Wiſdom, <hi>I have gotten</hi> (ſays <hi>Solomon,</hi> C. I. V. 16.) <hi>more Wiſdom than all they who have been before me in</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>yea, my heart had greater Experience of Wiſdom and Knowledge;</hi> but, in the very next Verſe he ſays—<hi>I perceived that this alſo was Vexation of Spirit; for in much Wiſdom is much Grief, and he that increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Knowledge increaſeth Sorrow.</hi> Not to ſpeak much of the Difficulties of acquiring Wiſdom here, and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but a tolerable Share of Knowledge; how many
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63324:6"/> Years are ſpent in providing the Memory with Words and Images; how many in applying Words to things; how many more in fitting them to underſtand Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herences, and making them attend to Conſequences and Connections? and when the Mind is thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with neceſſary previous Elements, what work is there, to diſpoſe it to ſee the Convenience and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of its purſuing Wiſdom? how much of Life is over-ſlipt, before it thinks there is any need of farther Underſtanding, and before it can be brought to ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that Buſineſs in good earneſt? and when it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd and reſolute, what Pains, what Trouble and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities are there in laying down one ſingle Prejudice and Prepoſſeſſion? what Labyrinths and Intricacies do we wander in, when we would ſolve ſome new or old Effects of Nature? how deep and dark are her Receſſes? how hidden and obſcure are all her Cauſes and her Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? how ſubtle and entangling are the Nets of Error? how hard it is to ſeparate it from Truth; and how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd is Truth it ſelf in Controverſies and Diſputes? what a World of ſtaggering Probabilities on both ſides? and if a Man be ſetled with ſome fair Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and ſpecious Amuſements to Day, he is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps awakened by ſome ſharper and ſeverer Truths to Morrow, and the next Day's Thoughts put him again into a State of new Diſtraction and Irreſolution. To name no more, How hard is it to fix on any point, and to purſue it cloſely to the end? what infinite Labours and almoſt inſuperable Difficulties, does our inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and curious Itch of new Varieties put us upon; ſo that we paſs our Lives away in our Diverſions and Excurſions after collateral things, and loſe the very Sight and Scent of our main Purpoſe and Deſign? not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63324:7"/> to dwell, I ſay, long on theſe and on a Thouſand, and Ten Thouſand other Difficulties that attend the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of Wiſdom, and the getting a little more than ordinary Underſtanding. Not to enlarge too far upon the Troubles of poſſeſſing Wiſdom; its moſt inſatiable and voracious Appetite; its never being fill'd with any Addition to it. Thirſt after Knowledge is like that of Riches, and increaſes with it. It is, (as one hath well expreſſed it) like Drink to a Man in a Fever, which inflames the Appetite to a more impetuous craving; which is a very painful and uneaſy State, and ſhews the Vanity and unſatisfying Emptineſs of Knowledge, and brings Abundance of Vexation with it. Not to inſiſt on the reſt of the Diſquiets that attend it. The unreaſonable Fears it infuſes into the Soul, by ſcaring it with fantaſtick and imaginary Dangers, which may come to paſs; and perhaps would, if this World were governed according to the Rules of humane Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and an uniterrupted Train of reaſonable Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. The vaſt Deſires it fills us with, as well from the Conſideration of the Capacity and Comprehenſiveneſs of the Soul, as from the good Opinion it cheriſhes in Men of their Abilities: The Jealouſies it ſubjects Men to, from the ſame Reaſon, of making them ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited, and imagining ſufficient Honours and Reſpects are not paid them; with other Doubts, Impatiencies, and reſtleſs Emulations, which are, if not the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, yet the uſual Fruits of Wiſdom in Poſſeſſion: Beſides the ſouring and corrupting all that Gayety of Heart, and chearful Temper Men would otherwiſe be of; there being nothing more obſerved to make Men peeviſh, fretful and moroſe, impatient of Oppoſition, and imperious in Converſation, than a retir'd and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63324:7"/> Life, and a cloſe, ſevere way of Thinking, and Examining Matters.</p>
            <p>Not to inſiſt, at laſt, upon the danger there is of parting with this Knowledge Men have had in their poſſeſſion, in a very little time, by the Treachery of an unfaithful Memory, by the Accident of ſome ſtrong Diſeaſe, by the Dryneſs and Defects of Old Age; or, laſtly, by the Stroke of Death, after which, <hi>there is no more Remembrance of the Wiſe Man, than of the Fool; ſeeing that which now is, in the Days to come ſhall be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi> Not to inſiſt at large on all theſe, the painfulneſs of getting, the trouble of poſſeſſing, and the fear of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Wiſdom, all which do moſt abundantly argue its Vanity, we may ſuppoſe a Man, inſpired as <hi>Solomon,</hi> with Natural Wiſdom, and fully aſſured of keeping it till Death; yet it would not much contribute to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing happy in this Life.</p>
            <p>There is no Man, let him place his Happineſs in what he will, but either wants an Acceſſion of ſome new Thing he deſires, or the Removal of ſome old In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, or elſe a firm Continuance of the State he is already in; all which depending moſtly on the Wills of other Men, or on Accidents in Nature, which are varying every Day, uncertain, unſecure to be relied upon, not poſſible to be fore-ſeen, or, if fore-ſeen, to be prevented. It is not the Wiſdom of this World that can make or keep Men happy.</p>
            <p>What if the wiſeſt Man on Earth, wants, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat his Happineſs, a new Acceſſion of Eſtate, or an Inheritor to what he has, or Vertue, Wiſdom and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety in that Inheritor; which way ſhall Wiſdom and Underſtanding make proviſion of theſe things? Since, as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Prov. 9. 11. That Bread is not to the</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:63324:8"/> 
               <hi>Wiſe, nor yet Riches to Men of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, nor yet Favour to Men of Skill; but Time and Chance happeneth to them all.</hi> But if he ſhould have an Eſtate, and want an Heir, he would, it may be, do like <hi>Solomon, Ch. 18. Hate all his Labour which he had taken under the Sun, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was to leave it to a Stranger after him.</hi> But if it were a Son, <hi>Who knoweth whether he ſhall be a wiſe Man, or a Fool? Yet he ſhall have Rule over all my Labour, wherein I have laboured, and ſhewn my ſelf wiſe under the Sun: And, ſurely, this is alſo Vanity.</hi> And let no Man think it is unworthy of a wiſe Man, or below him, to deſire, or ſet his Heart upon ſuch things as theſe; or want them, to compleat his Happineſs: For <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Experience, and a very little Inſight into Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will aſſure him it is otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>What if the wiſeſt Man living want to remove ſome Bar and Hindrance to his Happineſs, (for it is with wiſe Men ſometimes, as it was with proud <hi>Haman;</hi> who, though he was the Second Perſon of an Hundred Twenty Seven Provinces, and received the Bows and Adorations of all the Princes in the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> yet was not quiet for the Stiffneſs of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> one inconſiderable <hi>Jew,)</hi> they want ſome little matter or other in their way to be removed, that troubles all their Peace and Quiet: And their Wiſdom commonly is as little able to help them out, as Folly it ſelf would be; whether the Bar be put by natural Accidents, or by the Obſtinacy and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of ſome Reaſonable Agents.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, Of Accidents: 'Tis acknowledged, that <hi>no Wiſdom is a Match for Chance:</hi> But for the latter, Oppoſition of Men; one might think that Wiſdom might deal well enough with that; but the contrary is commonly ſeen: For, What if a Man know both the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63324:8"/> Tempers, and the ſeveral Intereſts of Men, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the whole Art of Buſineſs, and the Management of practical Affairs, ſince it happens very frequently, that the Paſſions and Inclinations of Men do apparently prevail againſt their true Intereſt; ſo that, to deal with them in the way of Reaſon, is, to loſe ones Labour on one hand; and ſometimes Intereſt prevails againſt the ſtrongeſt Inclinations, and the Bent of all their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: So that to deal with them in the way of Nature, is to loſe ones Labour on the other ſide: And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſome unreaſonable Pet, ſome trifling Jealouſie, and ſome ill-grounded Errour, prevails againſt Men's Intereſt and Inclinations, and frequently their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments too. So that if a Man's Happineſs depend upon his being able to deal with others, (as it often does,) it is, at leaſt, an even, Lay, that the ſuperior Wiſdom ſhall not be ſucceſsful: And if he chance to light upon one that is as wiſe as himſelf, there is ſome Reaſon ſeen why he does not gain his Point, but no great Comfort in the Conſideration.</p>
            <p>But if, in the Third Place, a Man's Happineſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a Continuance in the State he is already in, it is not all the Wiſdom of the World that can ſecure it to him. What Wiſdom is it that ſecures Men from ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Affections on the periſhing Things of this Life? Where is the Philoſophy that can hinder a Man from loving his Eſtate, or his Friends, immoderately? What Art or Underſtanding calls Men off from doting on their Children, from liking even every thing they ſay or do, from finding Wit in all their Words, and Grace and Comlineſs in every Action? So that, when Death deprives them of their Friends, their Favourites, or their Children, their Sorrows are then multiplied,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63324:9"/> according to their fooliſh Fancies; and they have then a number of moſt ſolid, true, ſubſtantial Torments and Regrets, equal to that of their imaginary and conceited Pleaſures; and in this Caſe, they loſe much more than ever they truly had: For, wretched is the After-Game that wiſe Men play, as well as Fools, on theſe Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: And there is no greater Miſtake, than to think, that the Wiſdom of this World (of which I have all along been ſpeaking) is a Preſervative againſt the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of unreaſonable and unruly Sorrows. For, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be, that wiſe Men think they know the value of their Loſſes better than the reſt; or whether their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are refined by Speculation, and they become there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by more ſuſceptible of theſe ſad Impreſſions; or from what other Reaſon, they are commonly more ſtricken with thoſe Accidents than other Men, and more impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and untoward under them. So that, upon a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Recollection, 'tis an hard thing to find the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Worldly Wiſdom, above the Plainneſs and Simplicity of common Men: It contributes as little to Men's Happineſs; <hi>it is altogether Vanity and Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if it be thus with Wiſdom, (as might be proved from endleſs Inſtances,) which is, without Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and without Compariſon, infinitely ſuperior to either Pleaſure, Honours, or Riches, there will be leſs need of enlarging much on any of them, or proving them improper for the procuring or preſerving Men's Happineſs. But becauſe the World is in poſſeſſion of other Opinions of theſe things; and more Men live by Example, than by Rules of Reaſon; and are more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of Pleaſures, and the reſt, than capable of being Wiſe; a Word or two of each of them.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:63324:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> Therefore of Pleaſures: It is certain, That the Happineſs of this Life is that (and no other than that) which Men eſteem their Hapineſs; ſo that Men are never the more or leſs happy for placing their Content and Pleaſure in things ſolid, or light, ridiculous or grave, ſuperficial or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial; becauſe it is the Opinion Men have of things, and not the things themſelves that make Men happy. He that is worth 100000 <hi>l.</hi> yet thinks it is too little for his Purpoſes and Ends, is not happier than he that is Maſter of an 100 <hi>l.</hi> and thinks it is enough for him. He that has all the World, beſides the particular thing he wants, is ſtill unhappy, if he place his Happineſs in what he wants. So that 'tis falſe and fooliſh too, to deny the Happineſs of this Life, to conſiſt in <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> if by Pleaſure we would only mean <hi>a State of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pleas'd, a Reſt and Acquieſcence of the Mind in the Condition Men are in.</hi> And <hi>Epicurus,</hi> fairly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, was in the right, before the Oracles of God declared the contrary; if they too did not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only change the Particulars, in which Men ought to ſeek and Place their Pleaſures and their Happineſs, and determined them to things cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, conſtant, ſolid, and more durable, than the Light of natural Reaſon could diſcover to them. And therefore, when King <hi>Solomon</hi> declaims a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Pleaſures; and ſays, <hi>they are Vanity and Vexation of Spirit,</hi> he means eſpecially Mens cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Delights, their wicked and unlawful Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and thoſe polluted Joys that ruine both the Soul and Body, and which by way of Eminency,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63324:10"/> have gotten the Name of <hi>Pleaſure</hi> fixt peculiar to them. But when he ſpeaks of the Vanity of other innocent Diverſions and Delights, it is then with Reſpect to their Shortneſs and Uncertainty; their Emptineſs and diſſatisfying Nature; the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable Returns they make to Men's Deſires, the Pains they are at to compaſs them, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiets and Impatiencies of waiting for them, and the ſpeedy Flights they take from them; So that 'tis hard to ſay, or name the Point of Time, in which they exiſt. And as little can be ſaid in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of <hi>Honours</hi> or of <hi>Riches.</hi> They are indeed, both of them exceeding uſeful and exceeding ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the World, but they are much more ſerviceable to Others than to their own Maſters: <hi>they</hi> are commonly the laſt People they make hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, if at all: What ſerves the Pomp and Honour of a Coronet, the Veneration of a Mitre, and the Terror of a Judge to them themſelves? they are ſerviceable to the keeping Dignity and Decency in the Commonwealth, to the preſerving Unity and Order in the Church, and to the Security of Men's Lives and Families, and Reputations and Eſtates; but all the Benefit their Maſters find in them, is from the Reflection of thoſe Honours from the meaneſt and moſt miſerable People: And if their Servants and Dependants are not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py or reſpected, it is manifeſt they think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſhonour'd and abus'd; and conſequently their Happineſs which is placed in theſe things, is exceedingly precarious, and in every Man's Power to interrupt and ſpoil. And beſides, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63324:10"/> Happineſs of being Honourable, or very Rich, is much abated by the Reſtraint that is laid upon Men of owning or confeſſing it. For whatever other Men, or whatever a Man thinks of himſelf yet it is not come to that paſs yet, that Men dare pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly boaſt themſelves happy for either Honours or Riches. They rather chuſe to paſs ſome ſober, mortifying Sentence on thoſe States, and depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Miſchiefs that do commonly attend them.</p>
            <p>Now though Men underſtand them pretty well, yet 'tis ſome kind of Trouble to conceal their Happineſs, and not to tell, in what their Vanity and Folly do moſt abound. Not to enumerate the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Misfortunes theſe two States ſubject Men to, of being inſolent, oppreſſive, vain, luxurious, thoughtleſs, and Abundance of other Miſchiefs that conſpire againſt Men's Happineſs in theſe Conditions; few are the Inſtances whom Wealth and Honours have made happier than they were before, and many of thoſe whom thoſe two States have betray'd and ruin'd. But,</p>
            <p>II. Although theſe ſeveral things would really much conduce to the bettering Men's Conditions, and procuring to them Happineſs, yet Man would be but little better for them, becauſe no Man knows what is truly good for him in this Life, and moſt convenient to the attaining of that End. Though all of them ſhould in their own Natures, and in the Opinion of the World, be very good, and fitted to make their Maſters happy, yet the Circumſtances of Men's Affairs are ſo different
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63324:11"/> and intricate, and the Tempers of Men ſo hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourſom and uncertain, and the Accidents of Fortune ſo ſtrange and many, that, it may be, that which would make Ten Thouſand People happy ſhall contribute to one Man's Miſery: That which would make a Man happy this Day, ſhall to Morrow perhaps undo him. Nay, That in which Men have been happy many Years, is that which will at laſt turn to their greateſt Grief and Miſery. So ſhort is our Fore-ſight, and ſo vain and weak all our Endeavours, either to wiſh for, to purſue, or to preſerve what is truly good for us in this Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What wilt thou give me,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Abraham</hi> to God,) <hi>ſeeing I am Childleſs?</hi> When God had hardly made an end of promiſing <hi>to be his Shield, and his exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great Reward:</hi> As if it had hardly been in God's Power to make him happy any other Way, than by giving him an Heir, inſtead of <hi>Eliezer</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus.</hi> But when the Day of Trial and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation came, and this ſo long'd for Heir was to be ſacrificed and killed by him himſelf, there is no doubt but the Torment of that Thought did far exceed all the Delights that he had ever ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in that Son; and he was ſo far from think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Son would make him happy, that he found it was the only thing that could reduce him to the extreameſt Miſery a Mortal Man is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of.</p>
            <p>What could be more honourable for <hi>Jephthah,</hi> than from a wretched and deſpiſed Outlawry, to be intreated by the Elders of his People to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63324:11"/> and take the Rule of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into his Hands? What Vows and Prayers could ſeem more proper and convenient, both for <hi>Iſrael</hi> and himſelf, than Vows and Prayers for victory? Who is there, that, in thoſe his Circumſtances, can (even in Fancy) think that any thing was half ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to compleat his Happineſs, as Conqueſt over <hi>Ammon?</hi> And who but would have thought that grateful Offer which he made to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his going out to fight, might have been a kind of Tye and Obligation to have both gotten and ſecured him Happineſs? Yet all was contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: He had better have continued a deſpis'd Exile, or periſhed by the Sword of <hi>Ammon;</hi> for the Sun that roſe upon his Victory, and ſaw not an happier Man in all the Hoſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> nor a more glorious and triumphant Conqueror elſewhere, yet ſhut not in at Even, a more deplorable and wretched Creature.</p>
            <p>One Man fanſies, That if he had but an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, he were compleatly happy; he would uſe it with great Temperance himſelf, and do abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Good to others. He finds himſelf diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to do a great many hoſpitable and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous things; but wants Supplies agreeing to the Largeneſs of his Heart: He finds his Bowels Yearn at Objects of Compaſſion, and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them if he could: He only ſeeks for Riches, to oblige Mankind, and conciliate the Favour of God, and be entirely happy. But if, by Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or Induſtry, he does grow rich, his Heart and Purpoſes are commonly changed with his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63324:12"/> Condition, or his Deſires grow even with his Subſtance, and he is ſtill as unable to do the good he deſired to do, as before; the Poor are ſtill as poor and empty as they were, though his Bowels ſtill yearn on, and the Man perſwades himſelf he longs to be doing good, but, to his great Diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, wants Ability. This is the beſt of the Caſe, That a Man with his Riches does no harm altho he does no good; but it ſeldom reſts here, he is either tempted to forget God, and ſacrifice to his own Draggs, or falls by degrees into a State of Luxury and all Exceſs, and makes the things that ſhould have been for his Good, an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of his falling; and is to his coſt convinced, That 'tis better to continue Poor, with good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, than Rich without them; or with them, when they come alone; and that he was not made to be happy by Riches, but was miſtaken in the Means of compaſſing his End.</p>
            <p>Another Man believes a Place of Honour and Authority, would make up all his Wants, and compleat his Happineſs, and thinks withal, he ſhould be capacitated to do a great deal of Service to his Country in it; he ſhould right the wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and relieve the oppreſſed, and do Juſtice to the Poor and Needy, with Abundance of other notable good Turns: But when he is in Honour and Authority, he grows it may be proud and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent, regards not right or wrong ſo much as Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Convenience, uſes his Intereſt and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to private Ends and evil Purpoſes; and is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being happier in that higher Station, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63324:12"/> more involved in Troubles, and perplex'd in Mind: And when he turns him to his inſide, ſees he was not made for Honours and great Places, and that his clambring upwards brought him not to Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, but to the Danger of a great Fall, and an uneaſy Seat in the mean while.</p>
            <p>Another thinks, his Good might be procur'd, by Oratory and the Power of Eloquence, and ſpends his Lamps and Nights, in reading the Works of the great Maſters of that Faculty, and turning over <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Demoſthenes;</hi> but had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpend an Hour or two in reading of their Lives and Ends. To ſee to what unworthy Purpoſes thoſe mighty Parts were oft abuſed, what ſoul and wicked Acts, thoſe Streams of Eloquence were to waſh away: what Emulations, Strifes, Contentions and Debates they were perpetually engaged in, and how fatal it was to both, <hi>to ſpeak beyond Compariſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beſt Tongues have the moſt Cauſes, but they have commonly the worſt too; and if they get greater Eſtates, they get the more ill Will and Odium with them. And 'tis hardly poſſible for them to thrive exceedingly, but to the Wrong of ſome and the Undoing of others. And who can think of being happy at the Expence of Truth and Juſtice, with any Comfort? Beſides, That an eloquent Tongue and fluent is an Allurement to talking much and holding up a Controverſy, which engages Men (in Oppoſition) to ſay a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unkind Things, and a great many fooliſh and a great many falſe, and if true, yet a great many
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63324:13"/> vain and unneceſſary things: It puts Men on the Rack, and often ſharpens the Wit to a degree of Keenneſs, that ends, without great Care, in Spite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Ill Nature; and, rather than want an Anſwer, or the making an handſom Period up, the Men of Wit and Fluence either chuſe, or happen, to loſe a faſt Friend, to diſoblige a great Man, and create a powerful Enmity. 'Tis like a ſharp and double-edg'd Knife; for one piece of Service it does its Maſter, it cuts his Fingers twice: And is ſo far from being fitted to make Men happy, that, as hardly One in a Thouſand attains to it, ſo 'tis hardly fit for One of an Hundred Thouſand.</p>
            <p>Another Man has a brave Heart, and ſtrong Sinews, and fanſies he is fitted for the Camp, and is deſign'd for Happineſs by Victories and Triumphs: But theſe are commonly the Dreams of Men at Eaſe, and the gay Reſults of Wine and good Company. He thinks not on the Toils and Hardſhips of that Life he meets withal upon Experience; the Straits of inconvenient Lodging, unwholſom Diet, and inclement Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; the perillous Attempts, the Inſolence of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, and Inferiors Mutinies; the ſpiteful E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations, the baſe and infamous Detractions; the wicked Notions of Religion, Morals, and true Honour; with the ridiculous Punctilio's of falſe: The ſevere revengeful Proſecutions of their idle Quarrels, the frequent Perjuries, the raging Blaſphemies, the horrible Enormities, Injuſtices, Rapes, and Beſtial Villainies, that commonly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63324:13"/> that Way of living. And yet even this, and all the reſt of the particular Conditions I have mentioned; and a great many more I have omitted, are, in the Opinion of the World, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make Men happy, with the Happineſs of this Life; and moſt of them, it may be, in their own Natures, would in ſome wiſe conduce to it, if it were not for our Blindneſs in ſeeking, our Ignorance in uſing, and our Folly in abuſing them. But,</p>
            <p>III. Though a Man ſhould be ſo fortunate as to light upon what was good for him at preſent, yet he would have no great Reaſon to exſult, becauſe his Good may be ſhort-liv'd, and change its Nature in a little time. <hi>For who can tell a Man what ſhall be after him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Head, does in ſome Meaſure fall in with the Other; and therefore, the leſs will ſerve to ſhew its Truth: And there is no Need of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this by Arguments or Deductions of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; there is only Need that Men ſhould open their Eyes and Ears, and attend to the Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that meet them every Day, of private and of publick Perſons, Families and Kingdoms, of Friends and Enemies, of Strangers and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances; how varying and uncertain all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of humane Life are; how little any Man can promiſe to himſelf or any elſe, the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the State he is already in; what ſudden Turns of Fortune thruſt Men out of their Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, which they imagined would have laſted them their Lives long; how many little unfore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63324:14"/> unthought of Accidents diſturb and quite unſettle the moſt fix'd and ſteddy Courſe of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs? How one unlucky lowring Day riſes and interrupts the Peace and Joy of our whole Lives, and makes them ſet in Sorrow and Deſpair. <hi>Boaſt not,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) of to Morrow, for thou canſt not tell what a Day may bring forth,</hi> Prov. 27. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aemilius Paulus</hi> was the greateſt and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt <hi>Roman</hi> in his time, for many Years; he had four Sons of great Hopes, and thinking two of them enough to propagate his Name, he gave the other two to be adopted into the braveſt and the nobleſt Families of <hi>Rome.</hi> And having conquered <hi>Perſeus</hi> and his Kingdoms, (the Foil of four preceding Generals) he brought the King and all his Children Captives, to grace his Triumph and victorious Entry into <hi>Rome.</hi> But mark, how Fate with them, and with us the Providence of God, diſpoſes of Events. The King deſign'd for Miſery, had all his Children then about him, the greateſt Comfort that his bad Eſtate could then bear, and the triumphant Victor loſt his eldeſt Son a few Days before his glorious Entry, and his youngeſt three Days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And though all Men thought before, that <hi>Perſeus</hi> was the greateſt and the ſaddeſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Uncertainty of humane Happineſs, yet then the Scene was chang'd, and all the Pity fell upon the Old and Miſerable Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:63324:14"/>
            <p>There is no body, ſcarce, whoſe Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or whoſe Reading does not furniſh him with Inſtances enough, and too many, of this nature, to confirm him in the Opinion, That the Happineſs of this Life is of a very ſhort and uncertain Continuance; and that no Man can have Reaſon to exult, or be ſecure in his preſent State, whilſt liable to ſo many lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Accidents, and ſurrounded with ſuch Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards.</p>
            <p>Since then (to conclude) all theſe things are ſo; ſince all is Vanity, and Vexation of Spirit; ſince there is no true Happineſs to be found in any of thoſe things, in which Men chiefly place it, What muſt become of us? Are we brought into this World to be perpetually deluded with the Hopes of being happy; yet nothing in it for to build thoſe Hopes upon? Muſt we wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up and down, like poor bewildred Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, in queſt of what we are never likely to obtain? Nature has planted in us all, we find, Hopes and Deſires of being happy, but we are left, it ſeems, to ſeek it where we can; and to feel it our, like hood-wink'd People, in perpetual Maze and Winding.</p>
            <p>And is there then no Anſwer to theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions in the Text?</p>
            <p>Yes, there is: And be that put theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, gives himſelf a full and ſatisfying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to them all; but it is ſo far from my Text, that I muſt but juſt repeat it; for it is the very laſt Sentence in the Book: <hi>Hear the</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63324:15"/> 
               <hi>Concluſion of the whole Matter: Fear God, and keep his Commandments; for God ſhall bring eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Work into Judgment, with every ſecret thing whether it be good, or whether it be evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you deſire to know what is good for Man in this Life, I will tell you: <hi>Fear God, and keep his Commandments:</hi> That is good for Man in this Life: <hi>All the Days of his vain Life, which he ſpendeth as a Shadow.</hi> Though <hi>there be many things that increaſe Vanity,</hi> yet there is ſomething he may faſten on, that has no Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, nor carries any manner of Vexation with it; and that is, <hi>Fearing God, and keeping his Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Time and Chance make mighty Work and Alteration in every other State, but have no Power to interrupt and ſpoil the Peace and Happineſs of this.</p>
            <p>And, as the Ignorance and great Uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of what may happen, argues the Vanity of all theſe other States, and is a great Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the purſuing them ſo warmly, and ſo zealouſly; <hi>(For who can tell a Man what ſhall be after him?)</hi> ſo the Certainty of what will follow the Neglect or the Performance of this our Duty of <hi>fearing God, and keeping his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> is as great an Encouragement on the other hand, to the doing it: And that is, the Certainty of Judgment; <hi>For God ſhall bring every Work into Judgment, with every ſecret thing, whether it be good or evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63324:15"/>
            <p>So that now we know <hi>what ſhall be after us.</hi> And knowing what is good for Man in <hi>this</hi> Life, is alſo good for him in <hi>another,</hi> we have our Anſwer to the Queſtions in the Text: And ſince we are convinced of the Vanity of all things elſe, let us, at laſt, attend to this divine Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the whole Matter, and <hi>fear God, and keep his Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
